Guide to the George Rowland Collins Papers MC.42
New York University Archives
George Rowland Collins Papers
1927-1959
1944-1959
New York University Archives
Collins, George Rowland, 1894-
Collins, Gladys R.
MC.42
0.25 Linear Feet in one half manuscript box
The collection contains speeches and published articles by George Rowland Collins, Dean of New York University's School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance between 1948 and 1955. In addition to his administrative role at the university, Collins was a 1922 alumnus of the NYU Graduate School of Business Administration and Professor of Marketing and Public Speaking.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Gladys R. Collins in July 1970. The accession number associated with this collection is 2019.013.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged chronologically in four folders.
Biographical Note
A native of Hubbard, Ohio, George Rowland Collins was born on August 27, 1894. He graduated from Macalester College in St. Paul, Minnesota in 1916 and earned the Master of Arts degree from Harvard University four years later. In 1922 he was awarded an MBA from New York University (NYU).
Collins began his teaching and administrative career at NYU in 1920. That year, he joined the faculty as an Instructor in public speaking in the English Department at University College. By 1923 he was Assistant Professor of Marketing and Public Speaking, rising to Associate Professor the following year, and to Professor of Marketing in 1926. One year later, Professor Collins was appointed Assistant Dean of the School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance. He became Associate Dean in 1931. Upon the retirement of A. Wellington Taylor in 1943, Collins was appointed Acting Dean of the Graduate School of Business Administration, as well as Acting Director of the Wall Street Division of the School of Commerce. The following year he was appointed to the deanship of GBA and the directorship of the Wall Street Division.
Dean Collins' dual administrative responsibilities in GBA and Commerce increased in 1948 when, upon the retirement of Dean John T. Madden, Chancellor Harry W. Chase selected Collins Acting Dean of the School of Commerce. In October 1948 he was appointed Dean and served in that capacity until 1955, when he relinquished the office in order to devote his energy to conducting a major fundraising campaign to gain new quarters for GBA. He was replaced at the School of Commerce by Thomas L. Norton. Collins continued as Dean of GBA until his retirement in June 1959. He died on October 10, 1968.
Scope and Contents
The majority of the speeches included in this collection are remarks presented by Dean Collins to faculty, students, and alumni groups between 1927 and 1959, and take the form of handwritten and typed manuscripts and cards. The collection also includes several published articles, among them "Role of the Collegiate School of Business in Higher Education" (1950) and the Beta Gamma Sigma Address for 1959.
Separated Materials
These speeches and articles are part of a larger donation of material presented to the New York University Archives in July 1970 by Gladys R. Collins, the wife of George Rowland Collins. Included among this material and placed elsewhere in the Archives are Annual Reports to the Chancellor for the Graduate School of Business Administration, 1944/1945 and 1952/1953 through 1958/1959; Annual Reports for the School of Commerce, 1948/1949 and 1950/1951 through 1952/1953; four publications used for promotion in the GBA Building Fund Campaign; three scrapbooks, publications, and photographs from the Golden Anniversary of the School of Commerce, 1950 (RG 11); and photographs of University College English department, 1921/1922, School of Commerce Faculty Dinner, 1936, Commerce Gridiron Dinner, 1937, and a dinner honoring George Burton Hotchkiss, 1949 (see Photograph Collection).
Speeches (documents); Collins, Gladys R.; Hotchkiss, George Burton, 1884-1953; New York University. Graduate School of Business Administration
- Remarks at Annual Gridiron Dinner honoring Dean Edward J. Kilduff, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Remarks at the 18th Annual Dinner of Delta Mu Delta, School of Commerce Honor Society (preceding Beta Gamma Sigma), honorary membership presented to Thomas B. Watson, President of IBM, 1930-12-13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Remarks at the Annual Alumni Dinner in honor of the appointment of Herbert M. Schiffer as Assistant Dean of the School of Commerce, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Remarks at the Annual Dinner of Beta Gama Sigma, when presenting for honorary membership Edward R. Stettinius, Jr., Chairman of the Board of the United States Steel Corporation, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Remarks of the Alumni Association Meeting marking for Dean Collins the close of one academic year of service as Acting Dean of the Graduate School of Business Administration, 1944-06 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- NYU Press Release: "Dr. G. Rowland Collins Named Dean of New York University Graduate School of Business Administration", 1944-06-28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Founders' Day, Alpha Kappa Psi, "Town and Gown", 1945-12-14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Remarks at a Testimonial Dinner honoring Dean Edward J. Kilduff on his promotion to Associate Dean at the School of Commerce, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Remarks at Alpha Delta Sigma Dinner, 1947-12-19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Remarks by Dean George Rowland Collins on the occasion of a Dinner in his honor given by the New York University School of Commerce Alumni Association, 1948-11-30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Remarks at Money Marketeers' Dinner, when accepting the Marcus Nadler Prize Key Award in the name of the Graduate School of Business Administration, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Role of the Collegiate School of Business in Higher Education." Intercom (Official magazine of the School of Commerce), Vol. 5, No. 1, p. 9, 1950-01 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "The Next Fifty Years," News Workshop, Vol. 1, No. 3, pp. 1-2, 1950 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Remarks at the Pre-Commencement Ceremony of the Graduate School of Business Administration, 1951-06 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Remarks at Annual Alumni Association Dinner, School of Commerce, honoring the 25th service birthday of more than fifty faculty members, 1951-04-10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "The True Scholar," Proceedings of the Nineteenth Annual Dinner of Beta Gamma Sigma (New York University Business Series No. 9), pp. 9-14, 1952-02-14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Remarks by Dean G. Rowland Collins at the Dedication of the Dean Herbert M. Schiffer Conference Room, School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance, New York University, 1954-02-04 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Remarks at First Alumni Homecoming Day, Graduate School of Business Administration, 1954-03-20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Remarks at Dean's Day Homecoming Conference, Graduate School of Business Administration, 1957-02-16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Remarks at the Annual Alumni Dinner, Graduate School of Business Administration, 1958-06-02 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Article for Newsletter of the Graduate School of Business Administration, 1958-06-18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Remarks at Dean's Day Homecoming Conference, Graduate School of Business Administration, 1959 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Remarks by G. Rowland Collins, in honor of his being tendered by the Association of Past Presidents of the Student Councils of the School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance of New York University, 1959-04-15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Remarks at Testimonial Dinner in honor of Dean Collins at the time of his retirement, Graduate School of Business Administration, 1959-04-28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Remarks at the Board of Trustees Dinner, 1959-06-09 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Beta Gamma Sigma Address," Beta Gamma Sigma Exchange, Vol. XLIII, No. 2, Serial No. 129, pp. 9-15, 1959 Summer (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Remarks made when presenting Reuben Harold Bach, Executive Bank Vice President, for honorary degree of Doctor of Humane Letters (institution unidentified, but not NYU), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Remarks by Dean G. Rowland Collins at the Unveiling of an Oil Portrait of Professor George Burton Hotchkiss - deceased, School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance, New York University, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 4)